Mammoth Miners Memorial Oral History Collection 2003-2004
University of Arizona Library Special Collections
Mammoth Miners Memorial Oral History Collection 2003-2004
MS 398
Ross, Renee
Papers, 2003-2004. This collection contains audio cassettes of recorded interviews with former miners of the San Manuel mine near Mammoth, Arizona. Also included are the transcripts of these tapes. Renee Ross, project manager of the Mammoth Miners Memorial Oral History Project interviews former miners on topics such as folklore, women in mining, pay, safety, administration, strikes and others.
1 linear foot
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The Mammoth Miners Memorial Oral History Collection memorializes the experiences of underground copper miners in the Mammoth, Arizona area and particularly workers in the San Manuel Mine. The San Manuel Mine, located 45 miles northeast of Tucson, opened in 1952 and by the time its closure was announced by new owner BHP Billiton in 1999 had mined a record breaking 14 billion tons of ore and was the largest underground copper mine in the country. Around 2,200 miners were employed to mine 356 miles of tunnels. The mine and its predecessors supported the nearby town of Mammoth, Arizona where many workers lived. In 2003 the mine officially stopped production and the remaining mining structures were demolished. The Mammoth Miners Memorial group was formed to commemorate the experience of these miners and the more than 50 men who lost their lives in the San Manuel mine.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series
Series 1: Transcripts, 2003-2004
Series 2: Audio Cassettes, undated
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains transcripts of recorded interviews with 22 former San Manuel miners (including a female miner) and two wives of miners. Topics covered include mining folklore, women in mining, pranks, mining terminology, rescue and safety, nicknames, strikes, administration, pay, life in Mammoth, and many others. Also included are 29 audio cassettes of recorded interviews with former miners.
Mammoth (Ariz.) - History.; Mines and mineral resources - San Manuel (Ariz.) - History.; Copper mines and mining - Arizona - History - 20th century.; Mines and mineral resources - Arizona - History - 20th century.; Copper miners - Arizona - San Manuel - Interviews.; Copper miners - History - Sources.; Oral history - Arizona - San Manuel.; Borboa, Victor - Interviews.; Garcia, Mick - Interviews.; Gomez, Vern - Interviews.; Gutierrez, Janet - Interviews.; Lutich, John - Interviews.; Miranda, Rodolfo - Interviews.; Ramirez, Enrique - Interviews.; Ramirez, Mary - Interviews.; Ross, Stephen - Interviews.; Swanson, Art - Interviews.; Thomas, Betty - Interviews.; Thomas, Lloyd - Interviews.; 1975-1999.
Container List
- Transcripts 2003-2004
  Arrangement: Alphabetical by last name. This series contains transcripts of recorded interviews with former miners of the San Manuel mine.
  - Robert Adams. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ray Blonigan. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Victor Borboa. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Philip Castro. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Vin Coxon. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brian David. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Murrel Derrick. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Richard Evans. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mick Garcia. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Vern Gomez. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jack Gorham. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Janet Gutierrez. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bob Hamill. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - John Lutich. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rodolfo Miranda. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Marion Mario Pina. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Enrique Ramirez. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mary Ramirez. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Stephen Ross. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Art Swanson. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Betty Thomas. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lloyed Thomas. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Michael Thorson. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - John Traynor. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Audio Cassettes undated
  Arrangement: Alphabetical by last name. This series contains the original audio cassettes of recorded interviews with former miners.
  - Robert Adams. undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ray Blonigan. undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Victor Borboa, Tape 1. undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Victor Borboa, Tape 2. undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Philip Castro. undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Vin Coxon. undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brian David, Tape 1. undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brian David, Tape 2. undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Murrel Derrick. undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Richard Evans. undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mick Garcia. undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vern Gomez, Tape 1. undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vern Gomez, Tape 2. undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jack Gorham. undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Janet Gutierrez. undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bob Hamill. undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - John Lutich, Tape 1. undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - John Lutich, Tape 2. undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rodolfo Miranda. undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mario Pina. undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Enrique Ramirez, Tape 1. undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Enrique Ramirez, Tape 2. undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mary Ramirez. undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Stephen Ross. undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Art Swanson. undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Betty Thomas. undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lloyd Thomas. undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Mike Thorson. undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - John Traynor. undated (Box 2, Folder 29)